Guide to the Leather Goods, Plastics, Handbags and Novelty Workers Union, Local 1 Records and Photographs WAG.104
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leather Goods, Plastics, Handbags and Novelty Workers Union, Local 1 Records and Photographs
1936-1992
1960-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leather Goods, Plastics, Handbags and Novelty Workers' Union. Local 1 (New York, N.Y.)
Di Paola, Domenic
WAG.104
6.75 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 oversize folder.
Leather Goods, Plastics, Handbags and Novelty Workers Union, Local 1 Records and Photographs document the New York City union's activities in the 1970s and contain photographs of events from the 1930s through the 1980s.
Historical/Biographical Note
Pocketbook Workers Local 1 was organized in 1886 and the national union of which it was part had its antecedents in the upsurge of organization among Jewish needle trade workers in the decade following 1910. A 1916 general strike of leather goods workers resulted in the first signed contract with the New York Leather Goods Manufacturers Association in August 1918. Originally affiliated with the United Hebrew Trades, the local obtained a charter from the AFL as Federal Labor Union no. 17873 in 1926 and in 1937 as the International Ladies' Handbag, Pocketbook and Novelty Workers Union. A workforce of Jewish and Italian artisans working for such manufacturers as Coach Leather, as well as smaller novelty shops, has seen the introduction of Puerto Rican and African-American artisans. Many New York City shops have closed in recent decades. In 1992, Local 1 merged with United Food and Commercial Workers Local 342-50.
Related Archival Materials
Related materials at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives include oral history interviews with union president Domenic De Paola and pocketbook maker Max Goldheim in the New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection (OH 001). The Mordecai Barles Papers (WAG 183) contains documents related to Pocketbook Workers, Local 1.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Domenic di Paola, 1994. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1994.009 and 1994.012.
The accession numbers NPA 2001.073 and NPA 2001.074 are also associated with this collection.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by folder title. Records have not been arranged by an archivist and are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the International Ladies' Handbag, Pocketbook and Novelty Workers Union Local 1 are incomplete. Included in the collection are Executive Board minutes, 1968-1981; membership minutes, 1968-1977; negotiation and arbitration files from the 1970s; assorted newsletters, contracts, anniversary journals, and correspondence, mostly from the presidency of Domenic Di Paola. Photographs date from the 1930s through the 1980s and are mostly ceremonial. Photographs include those of union-sponsored medical procedures and union elections.
Photographs.; Black-and-white photographs.; Leather workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Jewish labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Collective labor agreements |x Leather industry |z New York (State) |z New York.; Leather Workers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Strikes and lockouts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Di Paola, Domenic; Leather Goods, Plastics, Handbags and Novelty Workers' Union. Local 1 (New York, N.Y.); Pocketbook Workers Union. Local 1 (New York, N.Y.); Polter, Rita; United Hebrew Trades; New York Leather Goods Manufacturers Association; Coach Leatherware (Firm); International Ladies Handbag, Pocketbook and Novelty Workers Union; United Food and Commercial Workers International Union. Local 342-50 (New York, N.Y.); Di Paola, Domenic
- Records: Bylaws, Newsletters, Negotiations, Arbitration Awards, Miscellaneous, circa 1970-1980 (Box 1)
- Records: Pension Agreements, Contracts, Miscellaneous, circa 1936-1977 (Box 2)
- Records: Executive Board Minutes, Membership Minutes, Merger Agreement with UFCW, circa 1950-1992 (Box 3)
- Records: Papers from Domenic Di Paola's Office, circa 1988-1994 (Box 4)
- 16th Ampire State Labor Management Exhibit, May 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- 4th Biennial Convention International Pocketbook Workers, Nov 1930 (Flat-file 7, Drawer 13)
- Associated Hospital Lists, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Ballot Voting for 15 Cent Increase Also Pictures of Puerto Rico Parade [includes negatives], Jun 1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Chairmen Meeting, Apr 1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- The Children's Village in Haifa, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Convention of the IHLB & Nov Workers Union, Jul 1954 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Cuts for Newspaper - Blue Cross, circa 1935 - 1950 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Elections - Voting, 1961 - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Elections - Voting, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Elections - Voting [includes negatives], 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Ephemera, 1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Framed Photograph - Eleanor Roosevelt, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Group Portrait, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Group Portraits with Identifications, undated (Box 4)
- Installation 1961-1964 Flu Shots 1961 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Letter, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Manhattan Center and Elections, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- March of Dimes, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Meeting of the Cotters Section [includes negatives], Apr 1961 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Nelson Rockefeller, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Nelson Rockefeller, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Mr. Lubliner and Officers, circa 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Original Photographs, circa 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Officers - Pocketbook Workers Local 1, Jan 1970 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Official Notice - Union Shop, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Oversize Photographs (Box 6)
- Pickets - 1st International Leather Goods Show, circa 1962 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Plaque - Medical Services, circa 1945-1955 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Photographs, circa 1940-1965 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Photographs, circa 1955-1965 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Photographs, circa 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Photographs, circa 1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Photographs, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Photographs, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Photographs, circa 1964 (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Photographs, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Photographs, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Photographs - Contract Negotiations, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Photograph - Meeting Joint Retirement Fund, Pocketbook and Workers Union, Local 1, Manhattan Center, Aug 18, 1955 (Oversize Box XOS 1)
- Photographs - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Photographs - Presentation of Plaque, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Photographs - Presentation of Alligator Bag to Mrs. Robert F. Wagner, Dec 1955 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Photographs - Purchase of Housing Bonds, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Photographs - State of Israel Bonds, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Photographs - Retirement Meeting, Aug 18, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Photographs - Shop Conferences - Negotiation Meetings, circa 1959-1964 (Box 5, Folder 48)
- Photographs - Welfare Fund, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 49)
- Pocketbook Workers, circa 1945-1960 (Box 5, Folder 50)
- Pocketbook and Workers Union, Local 1 - Delegates to the Triennial Convention, International Leather Goods Novelty Workers, Atlantic City, New Jersey, June 1957 (Flat-file 7, Drawer 14, Folder 1)
- Pocketbook Workers Union Project - Children's Village in Israel, May 1956 (Box 5, Folder 51)
- Red Cross Drive, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 52)
- Reception - Labor Day Parade, undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
- Speech for NY State, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 54)
- Trustee designation certificate for Joint Retirement Fund, 1957 (Box 2)
- Union Labor Life Ins Co Lists, circa 1950-1959 (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Union Labor Life Co Lists, circa 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 56)